We pick up today דף יט Daf Yud Tet and not דף
יז Daf Yud Zayin sorry I don't even know where I am
דף יט Daf Yud Tet thank you they look the same some
גמרות Gamarrahs them. We pick up today on דף יט Daf Yud
Tet
and it is about five lines down on the wide line. Okay
so we had been talking about being dealing with the burial of
a מת Meis which led us to a discussion about ways to
act in a cemetery that ציצית tsitsis out dragging on the floor
whether the מת Meis knows what is happening. And now because that
sort of led us to a digression about some two little אגדתות
Aggaditas at the end about about שמואל Shmuel was done somebody spoke
ill of שמואל Shmuel after he had died and a beam fell
from the roof of a building and cracked this guy's skull. So
that talks now we are talking about like respect shown to תלמידי
חכמים Talmidei Chachamim and speaking ill or thinking ill of תלמידי חכמים.
Talmidei Chachamim. So with that in mind five lines down on the
wide lines on יט עמוד א. Yud Tet Amud Aleph. ואמר רבי
יהושע בן לוי V'amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi so רבי יהושע בן
לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi says because we had just quoted רבי
יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi a minute ago also about
speaking thinking ill of תלמידי חכמים. Talmidei Chachamim. בעשרים וארבעה מקומות בית
דין מנדין על כבוד הרב B'esrim v'arba mekomot beis din menadin al
kvod harav in twenty-four places בית דין Beis Din will put somebody
in נידוי Niddui like a type of excommunication because of lack of
respect shown to a רב Rav to a Rabbi. וכולן שנינו במשנתנו
V'chulan sh'nin b'mishnasenu and they can all be found in the משנה.
Mishnah. אמר ליה רבי אליעזר Amar lei Rabbi Eliezer so רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer said היכא heicha where I don't see it anywhere in
the משנה Mishnah they say things. אמר ליה Amar lei וכי תשכח
v'chi tishkach
go figure it out go find it yourself. Right so נפק דק
ואשכח תלת nafak dak v'ashkach tlas
he went out he looked closely he was able to find three.
What three did he find that were referred to in a משנה?
Mishnah? המזלזל בנטילת ידים Hamizulzil b'netilas yadayim
somebody that sort of denigrates sort of shows disrespect for the need
of washing hands והמספר אחרי מיתתן של תלמידי חכמים v'hamesaper acharei mitasan
shel talmidei chachamim the phrase we had from before somebody who speaks
after the again מיתתן mitasan does not mean the bed from the
context it doesn't so it sort of means from the way they
are acting from their from some things like to be נוטה noteh
from the right path from their divergence when they are sort of
seen to be doing something off the path and you still are
speaking about it והמגיס דעתו כלפי מעלה v'hamigish da'ato klapei ma'alah somebody
who acts haughty towards God. Let's take a look at where these
three are in a משנה. Mishnah. והמספר אחרי מיתתן של תלמידי חכמים
Hamesaper acharei mitasan shel talmidei chachamim מאי mai so it is interesting
we are going a little out of order because the most recent
thing we had discussed was this phrase somebody who speaks ill after
the improper behavior of תלמידי חכמים Talmidei Chachamim דתנן d'isna הוא היה
אומר hu hayah omer he used to say this is עקביא בן
מהללאל Akavya ben Mahalalel excuse me בן מהללאל ben Mahalalel used to
say so where are we? Okay מהללאל Mahalalel I am just checking
the I do not know I am just going to check the
רש"י Rashi hold on one second right
okay fine anyway I
just one second right okay עקביא בן מהללאל Akavya ben Mahalalel used
to say הוא היה אומר hu hayah omer אם אין משקין לא
את הגיורת ולא את המשוחררת
im ein m'shakin
lo es hageyores v'lo es hamshuchreres that when the ritual of the
סוטה Sotah woman suspected of adultery her husband if she is a
convert or she is a freed slave you cannot make her drink
the סוטה Sotah water. Why? Because the פסוק pasuk says בני ישראל
B'nei Yisrael so בני ישראל B'nei Yisrael here is being read in
the narrow sense meaning naturally born Israel and not a convert or
a freed slave though interestingly רש"י Rashi says if you look at
רש"י Rashi
four lines down from the narrow line beginning of the narrow line
ולא הגיורת בני ישראל אמור בפרשה פרט לאשת גר ועבד משוחרר. v'lo
hageyores B'nei Yisrael amur b'parsha prat l'eshes ger v'eved m'shuchrar. So interestingly
גיורת geyores does not mean that she is a גיורת geyores or
that she is a freed slave but that it is בני ישראל
B'nei Yisrael who is her husband is her husband a slave a
freed slave or is her husband a convert? So anyway there is
a little question about exactly how whether referring to her or her
husband but let's see where the גמרא Gemara goes what the משנה
Mishnah goes with this. וחכמים אומרים Vachachamim omrim this is a משנה
Mishnah in עדיות Eduyos and the חכמים Chachamim say
משקין mashkin you can make her drink even in those cases. אמרו
לו Amru lo and they said to him מעשה בכרכמית שפחה משוחררת
בירושלים ma'aseh b'Karkamis shifchah m'shuchreres b'Yerushalayim here is why it really raises
questions about רש"י's Rashi interpretation because it says isn't there a story
of כרכמית Karkamis a freed slave woman in ירושלים Yerushalayim it is
hard to read that it means a woman married to a freed
slave okay anyway a freed slave woman in ירושלים Yerushalayim והשקוה שמעיה
ואבטליון v'hishkua Shmaya v'Avtalyon and שמעיה
ואבטליון Shmaya v'Avtalyon she was suspected by her husband and he was
brought into the ritual of סוטה Sotah and שמעיה ואבטליון Shmaya v'Avtalyon
ruled that she had to drink the water it does not literally
mean they made her drink it because they were not כהנים Kohanim
but they ruled that she had to drink the water so you
see you can do it. אמר להם Amar lahem so he said
back to them דוגמא השקוה dugma hishkua that no that was only
a דוגמא. dugma. What does that mean? So the two interpretations first
I will read you תוספות's Tosfos which is probably the simpler one
it says yeah it was a fake it was like sugar water
which basically means they made it look like she was drinking but
they did not really do
the. Which is an interesting answer, which A, makes the question what
motivated them to do it if you're not supposed to, and B,
what good would it be to do the procedure if it wouldn't
be effective? Like you know wouldn't that sort of placebo
effect would have caused 25%?
But there you go. So you think she'd really committed adultery, the
placebo effect would have caused her stomach to explode anyway. So that's
what תוספות Tosfos says. רש''י Rashi says, I mean that works better
in terms of the word, which is they fed her like a
mock. Some, something. רש''י Rashi says they were דוגמא, dugma, they were,
they did it for her because they were like she was. שמעיה
ואבטליון Shmaya and Avtalyon were גרים. gerim. So that's why, you're right,
they shouldn't have done it, but שמעיה ואבטליון, Shmaya and Avtalyon, so
they were concerned for their own and that's why they did it.
Now you can combine the two, you could say because they were
גרים gerim they wanted to do it, but because it was maybe
הלכתית halachically he's claiming not allowed, maybe they only did it with
a placebo. Okay, so you can combine the two explanations. But anyway
he said, you know, either way he's saying obviously something not complimentary
about שמעיה ואבטליון. Shmaya and Avtalyon. Either he's saying that they made
it look like they did it when they didn't, they faked it
out, or he's saying they ruled in a way they shouldn't have
ruled because they were partial. So what happened as a result of
making this claim about שמעיה ואבטליון? Shmaya and Avtalyon? So it says
ונידוהו, veniduhu, that they put him in נידוי, niduy, that they put
him in a type of חרם. cherem. How can you say such
a thing about שמעיה ואבטליון? Shmaya and Avtalyon? ומת בנידויו, umes beniduyo,
he died when he was still in this נידוי. niduy. He never,
you know, after, if a person is put into נידוי, niduy, there's
a way he goes and he makes up with the people that
he offended and then
they, this is עקביא בן מהללאל,
Akavia ben Mahalalel, עקביא בן מהללאל, Akavia ben Mahalalel, right. And then
they sort of reverse, you know, they annul his נידוי, niduy, they
permit, they release him from it. But he, he stood his ground.
And therefore, וסקל בית דין את ארונו. vesakal beis din es arono.
So what happens if a person dies in נידוי, niduy, so you
put a stone, maybe you put a stone on or you literally
stone his coffin. Which is pretty harsh, which is not just that
he's like you know he's on the outs but it's a type
of a virtual
act of stoning. So anyway, that's what they said. Yeah, look how
terrible it was that he made this claim and then he never
reversed it. So that's the proof of somebody who speaks ill of
תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim after their actions, maybe their questionable actions.
He was right.
How do you know? That was his claim.
Oh, you mean he
claimed, he's offering me a proof of that, that was just a
fake. How do you know? So they were very, so they thought
that that wasn't what happened and that he was, you know, making
disrepute about עקביא בן
מהללאל, Akavia ben Mahalalel, about שמעיה ואבטליון. Shmaya and Avtalyon.
Would it have been different if he would have known that they
had faked the water?
Well, that's a good question. Maybe he did know they did. You
know, it's always a question about who do you ask. According to
him, maybe he wasn't speculating, maybe he really did know, you know,
maybe they, everyone had a different interpretation about what happened. It happens
very often that there's a different interpretation, like we just quoted earlier
in the גמרא, Gemara, a famous discussion about שמאי והלל Shammai and
Hillel about, you know, eating in a סוכה sukkah with your table
in the house and they said, oh, you know, of course it's
okay because the elders of שמאי והלל Shammai and Hillel went to
visit so and so and he had his סוכה, sukkah, table in
the house and nobody said anything. And then שמאי Shammai said back,
what do you mean nobody said anything, they told him he wasn't
יוצא. yotzei. So you have the exact same event with two radically
different interpretations of exactly what happened. So it could be that nobody
is speculating, each person thinks they know. But from the חכמים's chachamim
perspective, that's not what happened and he's saying something ill
about
שמעיה ואבטליון Shmaya and Avtalyon and they had to defend their honor.
Question is whether you're allowed to criticize
the rabbis for something that they may have done, that they did
do.
Right, so that's a good point. And you know, so far the
גמרא Gemara has, I mean, so far the concern of the גמרא
Gemara has been that if they did something bad, you should assume
that they've done תשובה. teshuva. It doesn't mean that you can't assume
they've done something bad, but you should assume they've done תשובה. teshuva.
That's what we said yesterday. And here at least the sense one
gets is that their argument is that, you know, you interpreted what
they said in order to conform to your הלכה, halacha, but it
looks ill about them. But if they, but you know, I don't
think the גמרא Gemara is hesitant to, when there really is something
worth criticizing, criticizing. That happens a lot. But here I think the
question was that you're interpreting it in a bad way for them
so it works for you. Alright, so let's take a look. Anyway,
the גמרא Gemara is going to challenge that in a minute. So
let's take a look as it continues. והמזלזל בנטילת ידים, vehamizulzel binetilas
yadayim, if somebody shows disrespect for washing hands, מאי היא, mai hi,
what is this? דתנן, detnan, אמר רבי יהודה, amar Rabbi Yehuda, חס
ושלום. chas veshalom. So here was the response to this. חס ושלום
שעקביא בן מהללאל נתנדה, chas veshalom she'Akavia ben Mahalalel nisnadah, God forbid
that somebody of the, you know, of the importance of עקביא בן
מהללאל Akavia ben Mahalalel was put into נידוי. niduy. Either he never
would have said such a thing or B, if he would they
wouldn't have put him into נידוי. niduy. You know, somebody of his
importance would not have been died in נידוי niduy and put into
נידוי. niduy. שאין עזרה ננעלת על כל אדם מישראל בחכמה ובטהרה וביראת
חטא כעקביא בן מהללאל. she'ein azara nin'eles al kol adam mi'Yisrael bechochmah
uvetaharah uveyiras cheit ke'Akavia ben Mahalalel. When the Temple courtyard was closed
on פסח Pesach when all of the, you know, everybody. gathered to
bring their קרבן פסח Korban Pesach and they locked the doors so
you had basically the entire Jewish people, actually they did it in
three shifts. But in the temple courtyard, nobody there would have come
close or equaled עקביא בן מהללאל Akavya ben Mahalalel when it came
to wisdom, טהרה taharah purity, and יראת חטא yirat chet and fear
of sin. So meaning not only was he wise, but he was,
as טהרה taharah here probably means also metaphorically in terms of character
traits, but he never would have done anything improper. So it couldn't
have been him. That could not have been what happened. אלא מי
ניהו? Ela mi nihu? There is a story that they put a
certain sage into חרם, cherem, but it wasn't him. Who did they
put into חרם? cherem? את אלעזר בן חנוך. et Elazar ben Chanoch.
אלעזר בן חנוך, Elazar ben Chanoch, what did he do?
שפקפק בנטילת ידים. she-pikpek be-netilat yadayim. That he was disrespectful
of
washing the hands. He didn't bother doing it. He treated it, he
made light of it. He they put into נידוי. niddui. וכשמת u-keshe-met
and when he died, it doesn't tell you, that's a fascinating statement,
what would have motivated that? Right? I mean it's something that's obviously
a very serious thing in חז"ל. Chazal. But anyway, whatever it was,
he was not treating it respectfully. וכשמת שלחו בית דין והניחו אבן
גדולה על ארונו. u-keshe-met shalchu bet din ve-henichu even gedolah al arono.
And when he died, he died in his state of נידוי niddui
and they put a large stone, here they don't use the phrase
they stoned it, but they laid a large stone on his coffin.
ללמדך שכל המנודה ומת בנידויו בית דין סוקלין את ארונו. le-lamedcha she-kol
ha-menudeh u-met be-nidduyo bet din soklin et arono. Anybody put into חרם
cherem and who dies in that state, בית דין bet din so
they literally stone, but here we see what it means is they
place a stone on his coffin. So here there's a question who
they did, but presumably either act would have been deserving of it.
So since either act would have been deserving of it, you see
that these are two ways you can show disrespect to the rabbis,
one is to actually make a claim about the behavior of certain
rabbis that is disrespectful and maybe not accurate, and B is to
disrespect the תקנה takanah of the rabbis. Right? Now by the way,
that's very different than just violating, we're not saying anybody that violates
a rabbinic law is מזלזל בתלמידי חכמים mezalzel be-talmidei chachamim and to
be put in חרם. cherem. It's showing a disrespect, like why should
I do that, what it's only rabbinic, or something like that. So
that's the type of an issue that is a basic disrespect of
the authority of the rabbis, and that's this issue of נידוי. niddui.
So that's two. Number three, המגיס דעתו כלפי מעלה, ha-megis da'ato klapei
ma'alah, arrogance towards God or towards heaven. מאי היא? mai hi? דתנן:
de-tnan: שלחו לו שמעון בן שטח לחוני המעגל. shalchu lo Shimon ben
Shetach le-Choni HaMa'agel. You might know this, the famous story about חוני
Choni the circle-drawer, המעגל, HaMa'agel, right? That he makes a circle and
he says to God, right, he prays for rain and for- it's
a few drops and he says, God I don't want drops, I
want more, so then it becomes a torrent, he says God it's
not a torrent, that's too much. And basically he draws a little
circle, says I'm not going to step out of this circle until
you give me exactly what I want. Okay, so so they sent
to him, צריך אתה להתנדות. tzarich atah le-hitnadot. You deserve to be
put in חרם. cherem. ואילמלא חוני אתה ve-ilmalei Choni atah and were
you not חוני Choni who was obviously a person of, well we'll
see in a minute, but certainly somebody very favored by God, גוזרני
עליך נידוי. gozrani alecha niddui.
I would have put you into חרם. cherem. אבל מה אעשה? aval
mah e'eseh? What can I do? שאתה מתחטא לפני המקום. she-ata mitchateh
lifnei ha-Makom.
You are מתחטא mitchateh in front of God. Now what is מתחטא?
mitchateh? So רש"י Rashi here basically means, it means like
you're naughty, you step over the line before God, you misbehave in
front of God, some say it's a different interpretation but anyway, והוא
עושה לך רצונך. ve-hu oseh lecha retzonecha. And God loves you so
much that he doesn't care about your misbehavior, he does what you
want. כבן המתחטא לפני אביו ועושה לו רצונו. ke-ven ha-mitchateh lifnei aviv
ve-oseh lo retzono. Like a child who misbehaves and the father loves
the kid so much that he still does whatever the kid wants.
ועליך הכתוב אומר, ve-alecha ha-katuv omer, regarding you the פסוק pasuk says,
ישמח אביך ואמך ותגל יולדתך. yismach avicha ve-imecha ve-tagel yoledtecha.
So pretty interesting way of ending a statement that you deserve to
be put in חרם. cherem. Your father will rejoice and mother will
rejoice over you. You are loved so much by God that you
can get misbehave and get out of it. So therefore I'm not
going to put you in חרם cherem because obviously you are
favored by God. But you're deserving of it because of the way
you acted towards God. Now so again, it's interesting that that then
becomes a model
of that overstepping of the boundary and acting a little bit like
entitled. Really isn't arrogance, it's more like entitled towards God. I mean
you could say that's insolent, but המגיס דעתו ha-megis da'ato normally I
think has normally a sense of like arrogance and haughtiness, but here
there's an element of that, but I think it's predominantly a sense
of entitlement. Anyway, so you see that was deserving of נידוי. niddui.
So presumably if that's the way you act towards God then it's
deserving of נידוי niddui somehow by transference that becomes a model of
acting disrespectful towards rabbis or towards authority or religious authority or so.
גסות הרוח.
gasut ha-ruach.
אהה. aha. גסות דעת. gasut da'at.
אהה. aha. המגיס דעתו. ha-megis da'ato. יגסו לו ונתחטא. yigasu lo ve-nitchata.
You like so your spirit is fat, your spirit is coarse.
Right, so your belief is like.
You wanted it to be closer
to that sense of like entitlement or yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
Right. Right. I hear.
No, no, it's a good point. Right. Right, right, right.
No, it's a good point, the difference between גסות *gasus* and גסות
הרוח *gasus haruach*. Right. Okay, so anyway, those were the three. So
now we have, where were we? Okay. So that was what, that
was what שמעון בן שטח
Shimon
ben
Shetach *Shimon ben Shatach* sent to חוני המעגל Choni HaMa'agal. *Choni HaMa’agel*.
Where were we? Okay, fine. Okay, fine. So it says, okay, וסלקא
דהא איכא *v'salka d'ha ikka*, so that's three, but he said twenty-four.
But one minute, I can help you, I can add to the
list of three. We have דתניא רב יוסף תודוס Theodos איש רומי
*d'tanya Rav Yosef Tudos Ish Romi*. תודוס *Tudos*, man of Rome, Tudos
might be a Roman name, I don't know, but he הנהיג את
בני רומי לאכול גדיים מקולסים בלילי פסחים *hinhig es b'nei Romi le'echol
gedayim mekulasim b'leilei Pesachim*. So here, we know, you know, our practice
is you're not supposed to eat roast meat on the Seder night.
But actually the Mishnah in מקום שנהגו *Makom She'nahagu* says מקום שנהגו
לאכול צלי בלילי פסחים אוכלים *Makom she’nahagu le’echol tzali b'leilei Pesachim ochlim*.
That the place that they had the מנהג *minhag* to eat roast
meat on ערב פסח *Erev Pesach*, on Seder night, they would eat.
And presumably it doesn't just mean that they were allowed to eat,
but actually it was a place that they specifically had a practice
of eating roast meat. And I believe there's still some ספרדים *Sefardim*
that specifically eat roast lamb and roast meat on Seder night in
order to be a זכר לפסח *zecher l'Pesach*. But then there were
places where they resisted that and our practice, the אשכנזי *Ashkenazi* practice,
is against that because that is—it makes it too much seem like
you're actually מקריב *makriv* a קרבן פסח *Korban Pesach*. But there were
places where they actually wanted to have a sort of a simulated,
a pseudo-קרבן פסח *Korban Pesach* even without the קרבן פסח *Korban Pesach*.
And it went so far, not just to eat roast meat, but
to actually take a גדי *gedi* goat and to roast it whole
and to eat it on ערב פסח *Erev Pesach*. And do not,
ערב פסח *Erev Pesach*, eat it, you know, ליל פסח *Leil Pesach*,
eat it Seder night. So this is what this person did in
Rome, this תודוס איש רומי *Tudos Ish Romi*. And he not only
did it personally, but he actually tried to establish this practice. Let's
just read a little. It said הנהיג את בני רומי *hinhig es
b'nei Romi*. He, he like, established a practice in Rome and the
people of Rome, the Jews, לאכול גדיים מקולסים בלילי פסחים *le’echol gedayim
mekulasim b'leilei Pesachim*, to eat roasted goats—meaning the fully roasted, like the
whole goat over a spit, on Pesach night. שלח ליה שמעון בן
שטח Shimon ben Shetach *Shalach lei Shimon ben Shatach*. So שמעון בן
שטח Shimon ben Shetach, *Shimon ben Shatach*, who was also the one
who sent this message to חוני המעגל *Choni HaMa’agel*, he sent him
the following message: אלמלא תודוס אתה גוזרני עליך נידוי niduy. *ilmalei Tudos
atah gozrani alecha niduy*. So the same type of thing. I would
put you in חרם cherem *cherem*. Said it to חוני המעגל *Choni
HaMa’agel*, now he's telling it to him. If you were not Tudos,
which is such an important person—I don't know how we know elsewhere
about this person Tudos, but if you were not that person, maybe
it's like Theodos, Theodore, I don't know. Anyway, what? Because of the
fact that he was in a position to הנהיג *hinhig* them, he
was in a position to cause—establish a practice, right? So anyway, had
you were not who you are, your important status, so גוזרני עליך
נידוי niduy. *gozrani alecha niduy*, I would put you in חרם cherem,
*cherem*. שאתה מאכיל את ישראל קדשים בחוץ *she’atah ma’achil es Yisrael kodashim
bachutz*, because it's as if you're making them eat קרבנות *korbanos* outside
the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*. You are doing the practice so similar
to the bringing of a קרבן *korban* that you are, you know,
that you are making it look to them and to others like
they're bringing קרבנות *korbanos* outside of the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*. So
again, you see that because he acted in this way that again
is interpreted as—now it's very funny, you know, when you abstract something
so much that it doesn't become a meaningful category. So we sort
of started by saying that in twenty-four places, what was the phrase?
They were גוזר על כבוד הרב kevod harav, *gozer al kvod harav*.
כבוד הרב kevod harav *Kvod harav* now includes cases about, you know,
about a certain arrogance or entitlement towards God. כבוד kevod הרב *Kvod
harav* now is including a case about like doing a practice that
the rabbis disagreed with, but it wasn't even a time where the
other practice had been like firmly established. There were different practices out
there, you know? So it was a practice that they thought was
disruptive or they felt was, you know, they felt
was wrong and was, you know, bad policy. But all of a
sudden, how that becomes כבוד kavod הרב *kvod harav*, I'm not exactly
sure. Yes, Charlie, what do you have? So Americans, even to this
day, go out
on their lawn and sacrifice a goat on Pesach. So they actually
bring it. That's not just a—so right. And why would—and Rabbi Steinsaltz
leads a group in Israel every year that petitions the Israeli Supreme
Court for the right to bring a קרבן פסח *Korban Pesach* on
הר הבית *Har HaBayis*. Yeah. So why would this be
an illicit non-Jewish practice because it's in—it's bringing it—no, because he didn't
bring it as a קרבן *korban*. They went to their backyards and
they had their Pesach barbecue, right? Their Pesach barbecue was a—was a
גדי *gedi* goat over an open spit. Nobody was sprinkling blood, nobody
was making the מזבח *mizbeach*. But the rabbis just said, it's a
little bit too close for comfort. Sounds pretty close. Yeah, exactly. It
says an individual person has the power to impose a נידוי *niduy*,
but שמעון בן שטח *Shimon ben Shatach* was the אב בית דין
Beis Din *Av Beis Din*. Right. Let's stay in—right. But how is
that any individual rabbi today, if he wants to put a נידוי
*niduy* on someone, he can? So that's a good question. I'll just
answer briefly because there's other larger discussions about חרם cherem which are
not here. We're just going to wrap this up quickly. But there
are certain acts that are sort of predefined that if you do
these acts, like you're actually some people understand that certain acts you
automatically are put in חרם cherem even without any act of being
placed in חרם, but others, but according to others, if you do
these acts then you're deserving of חרם and sort of anybody presumably
who, you know, who you've offended or who represents, you know, the
sort of offended class can do that. There are other types of
things which, you know, require I mean, not like predefined violations, which
require more of like a decision and a בית דין and so
on. So it's you're right, it's a complicated question of exactly.
Absolutely. Right. Absolutely. And but so my basic my short answer to
you is, is that that's my short answer to you is is
that that's only for, you know, at least the way the הלכה
halacha develops, is things like that is only for predefined acts. Although
in the case here historically, it's sounded that way. It sounded like
this was an unexpected act and he did it and שמעון בן
שטח was responding. But you know, sometimes you don't know. שמעון בן
שטח was a serious rabbinic leader and maybe had other rabbis behind
him, they're just not mentioned in this.
And he was the נשיא.
Nasi. He was the נשיא. Nasi. Yes.
A predefined act automatically getting excommunicated, that's something in פרקי אבות. Pirkei
Avos. There are things in the Catholic Church that people are automatically
excommunicated without the Church doing anything. Right.
That's interesting. Yes, the רמב"ם Rambam says it about a few things
that the ראב"ד, Ra'avad, you know, disagrees. Mostly you find that you
have to be put in חרם by someone. But in terms of
Rifka's question, right, I mean שמעון בן שטח, right, thank you, is
was the נשיא, Nasi, so, you know, could be that he was
doing it, he had other rabbis behind him, they're just not mentioned,
but it's an important issue to raise. Let's continue in the גמרא.
Gemara. It says like this. So anyway, so you see why don't
you quote that? That was another case. So the גמרא Gemara says
דמשנתנו קאמינא. demishnasenu ka'amina. No, we're talking about the twenty-four cases in
the משנה. Mishnah. והא ברייתא היא. veha baraysa hi. That case about
the roasted goat, that was a ברייתא. baraysa. ומישתנא ליכא, umishnasena lika,
what, are there no more in the משנה? Mishnah? I'll still get
you more than the three. והא איכא, veha ika, how about הא
דתנן, ha detnan, what we taught? חתכו חוליות ונתן חול בין חוליא
לחוליא. chitcho chulyos venasan chol bein chulya lechulya.
This is the famous story about the תנורו של עכנאי, Tanuro shel
Achnai, the oven of עכנאי, Achnai, with רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. And
the question arose about an oven, so that was a pottery vessel
and could become טמא tamei and it became טמא. tamei. What happens
if you cut it into sections and you put sand between each
section? So as
would that then still retain the status of a pottery vessel and
retain its טומאה? tumah? Or because the sections are divided by sand
and the sand has not been put in a kiln and has
not been made into pottery, maybe it's not considered a pottery vessel
and therefore it loses its טומאה, tumah, does not become טמא. tamei.
So what is the story?
It doesn't matter.
Some שרץ sheretz touches it. Some טמא tamei thing touches it. Not
by טמא tamei by itself, but only pottery vessels can become טמא,
tamei, like stoneware cannot. This type of thing has sand between various
sort of, you know, sections, will that become is that a pottery
vessel or not? רבי אליעזר מטהר, Rabbi Eliezer metaher, רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer says it's טהור. tahor. וחכמים מטמאים, vechachamim metama'im, and the sages
say it's טמא. tamei. וזו היא תנורו של עכנאי. vezo hi tanuro
shel Achnai. And this is the famous תנורו של עכנאי. Tanuro shel
Achnai. Now that's a בבא מציעא סוגיא, Bava Metzia sugya, so we're
not going to get the whole story, but I'm sure many people
are aware, that's the one with the walls of the בית מדרש
Beis Medrash bending in and the heavenly voice coming out. We're not
doing that whole story. But anyway, מאי עכנאי, mai Achnai, what is
the meaning of the word עכנאי? Achnai? אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל,
Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Shmuel, מלמד שהקיפוהו הלכות כעכנא. melamed shehekifuho halachos
ke'achna. They circled around it with like הלכות, halachos, like a snake,
like a snake would sort of, you know, like a boa constrictor
somehow, they were all sort of, they were, you know, all there
was the rabbis were arguing around it about all different about the
הלכות halachos of this oven. וטימאוהו, vetim'uhu,
and they decided it was טמא, tamei, it was not this would
not make it טהור. tahor. ותניא, vesanya, באותו היום הביאו כל טהרות
שטיהר רבי אליעזר. beso hayom heviu kol taharos shetiher Rabbi Eliezer. And
again, the end of the story is that רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
stands his ground and asks the walls of the בית מדרש Beis
Medrash to go in and he refuses to reverse himself and he
says it's טהור tahor and the other rabbis overrule it. So it
says they had to sort of, you know, exert their authority against
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer because he's trying to quote God in his
defense and, you know, he's standing up resisting this sort of rabbinic
majority rule. So they have to make a show of their authority.
So what did they do? They took all of the things that
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer said were טהור, tahor, שרפום לפניו, serafum lefanav,
and they burned them in his face to show that they consider
them to be טמא. tamei. Okay, now again you even wonder, was
this only things that he said טהור tahor as a result of
having touched this type of an oven, or was it in general,
anything he ever said טהור tahor in the past they burned as
a way of sort of, you know, undermining his authority because he
is because he is sort of challenging theirs? ולבסוף ברכוהו. ulevasof berachuho.
And in the end, it literally means it says they blessed him,
but it's a euphemism, it means they put him in נידוי. So
here they put him in נידוי. Now this is a real case
of כבוד הרב, because here's a case that it's one thing to
argue, it's another thing that even after the argument you refuse to,
you know, to concede to the majority rule, that's the example of
זקן ממרא. zaken mamre. So here was something where they really was
threatening their authority and they had to. Actually this week's פרשה *parsha*.
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, ah, so you see there's another example. אפילו
הכי נידוי במתניתין לא תנן *afilu hachi nidui bemesnisan lo tnan*. Yes
the story, the case of the debate of תנור של עכנאי *Tanur
shel Achnai* is in the משנה *Mishna*. But the whole story afterwards
about the walls of the בית מדרש *Beis Medrash* and about what
they did to him, that's not in the משנה *Mishna*. So you
only, so in terms of what's exactly in the משנה *Mishna*, you
only have three examples of being put in חרם *cherem* for somehow
disrespecting or challenging כבוד הרב *kavod harav*. So where, so now we're
stuck with only three and originally the statement was twenty four. אתא
דכ"ד מקומות היכא דמשתכחא *ata dekaf-daled mekomos heicha demishtakcha*, how do you
get twenty four? גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says רבי Rebbe יהושע בן לוי
מדמי מילתא למילתא *Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi medamei milsa lemilsa*. רבי אלעזר
לא מדמי מילתא למילתא *Rabbi Elazar lo medamei milsa lemilsa*. רבי יהושע
בן לוי *Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi* makes analogies and רבי אלעזר *Rabbi
Elazar* didn't make analogies. So, yes, there were three cases where it
was explicit. And then there were like twenty one other cases where
you could say, oh, this case is just like that other case
over there about like נטילת ידיים *netilas yadayim*, and if they put
him in חרם *cherem* for נטילת ידיים *netilas yadayim* they probably put
this guy in חרם *cherem* too. And if they put in, so
any case that was similar to those three, he said oh, that's
another case where obviously they must have put him in חרם *cherem*
because I have the three that are my paradigm of when you're
put in חרם *cherem*. So okay, it's still a little, you know,
funny statement to say twenty four places they מנדין *menadin*, it's not
like the משנה *Mishna* tells us מנדין *menadin*, but I would assert
that they were put somebody in נידוי *nidui* for those cases. Anyway,
now we move back to the basic theme of קריאת שמע Krias
Shema *Krias Shema*. תנו רבנן tanu rabanan: *Tanu rabanan*: אין מוציאין את
המת סמוך לקריאת שמע Shema ואם התחילו אין מפסיקין *ein motzi'in es
hamess samuch leKrias Shema ve'im hitchilu ein mafsikin*. You don't take the
coffin out to bury right before the time of שמע Shema *Shema*
because then there's going to be whole issues about עוסק במצוה osek
bemitzvah. *osek bemitzvah*. So rather first say שמע Shema *Shema* and then
take the coffin out, so people don't have to lose that opportunity.
But if you take out then if you began, then you're not
מפסיק *mafsik*, because then you become עוסק במצוה osek bemitzvah *osek bemitzvah*.
איני *Eini*, is this really true? והא רב יוסף אפקוהו למת סמוך
לקריאת שמע Shema *veha Rav Yosef afkuhu lemesa samuch leKrias Shema*. Rav
Yosef, they took out his coffin right before שמע Shema *Shema*, they
didn't wait. So גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* says אדם חשוב שאני *adam chashuv
shani*. No, he was obviously a very important person, you did not
want to postpone his funeral proceeding even for this consideration. Now this
raises, you know, the general issue about עוסק במצוה osek bemitzvah פטור
patur. מן המצוה *osek bemitzvah patur min hamitzvah*, meaning once you're doing
one, you don't transfer to do another. Okay, but let's say you
have, it's your position to choose how to prioritize, which one am
I going to do? Shall I do this one first or that
one first? Well, you know, if I do this one first, then
I might not get a chance to do the other one. But
it's disrespectful, you know, there's a whole sort of sense of factors
that could go into making that initial choice of which one you
start with. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s basic first response is do
the one that you might not get a chance to finish if
you don't do it now, right? So if you start with the
מת meis *meis*, you might not get a chance to say the
שמע Shema *Shema*. So start with the שמע Shema. *Shema*. But if
there's another reason why you should be starting with the other one,
like it would be somehow disrespectful, you know, and the person's important,
then you go, then you do that. So it does raise an
interesting question about it's one thing when you're עוסק במצוה osek bemitzvah.
*osek bemitzvah*, but how do you decide which מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah* to
be עוסק *osek* in and what the types of potential trade-offs there
might be. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues with the
people that are doing this, שלפני המטה ושללאחרי המטה *shelelifnei hamita veshel'acharei
hamita*, in front of the coffin and behind it. So רש"י *Rashi*'s
גרסא *girsa* was, even if you're behind the coffin and you're, if
you're behind the coffin but you're still doing the מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah*,
you should still sneak off to say שמע *Shema* because you're not
as important as the people in front of the coffin. תוספות Tosafos
*Tosafos* had a simpler גרסא *girsa* of the משנה *Mishna*, which was
just whether you're behind or whether you're behind the coffin, the only
important question is are you needed to be part of the proceedings.
And if you're needed then you don't leave to say שמע *Shema*,
if you're not needed you slip off and you say שמע *Shema*.
So let's see the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. תנו רבנן *Tanu rabanan*: העוסקין
בהספד *ha'oskin behesped*, how about the people that are involved in the
eulogy? בזמן שהמת מוטל לפניהם *bizman shehamess mutal lifneihem*, if the coffin,
the corpse is right before them, נשמטין אחד אחד וקורין *nishmatin echad
echad vekorin*. Then they slip off one at a time and they
read, presumably you don't need them all to be there, right? Which
also raises an interesting question,
which is like how much is the audience considered עוסק במצוה osek
bemitzvah *osek bemitzvah*? You know, because you could say that also too,
if there's a הספד hasped, *hesped* there are a lot of people
around, they're also part of the sort of עוסק במצוה osek bemitzvah?
*osek bemitzvah*. You know, the משנה *Mishna* did not make it sort
of like, talked about the people in the row when it said
the people that are in right by the אבלים *aveilim* on the
inside and as they walk through the rows, they're עוסק במצוה osek
bemitzvah *osek bemitzvah*, the people on the outside can slip off, you
know, individually and say שמע *Shema*, but you would think having a
crowd is also like part of the עוסק במצוה osek bemitzvah *osek
bemitzvah*. Now it doesn't say everybody leaves. It says נשמטין אחד אחד
*nishmatin echad echad*, which means one at a time, so you know,
interesting question of like what does that mean to be, to what
degree are you עוסק במצוה *osek bemitzvah* in that context. אין המת
מוטל לפניהם *ein hamess mutal lifneihem*, if the מת meis *meis* isn't
in front of them, let's say it's in a different room, then
הן יושבין וקורין *hein yoshvin vekorin*, then they sit and they read
the קריאת שמע *Krias Shema*, והוא יושב ודומם v'hu yoshev v'domem *vehu
yoshev vedomem*, and he is silent. המה אומרים *hema omrim*, which presumably
means that although they're עוסקים בהספד oskim b'hasped, *oskim behesped* in the
sense like they're about to do the הספד hasped. *hesped*, maybe you
know, you first דאוון daven. *davven* before you do the הספד hasped
*hesped*, which again raises the question of at what stage are you
considered. So if the מת meis is there and you're all ready
to do the
הספד, hasped. then you're doing the הספד. But if the מת meis
isn't there, then you can first sort of say שמע and דאווען
daven again. The context is not clear. Maybe you could read it
so far to say if the מת meis isn't there, they're all
doing the הספד and then they say we're breaking for מנחה Mincha
or we're breaking for קריאת שמע and we're going to continue the
הספד. That obviously would seem very inappropriate. But again, what I'm trying
to do is reconcile the phrase of עוסקים בהספד, how much are
you already עוסק בהספד? osek b'hasped? It seems anyway the answer's somewhat
contextual. The more the מת meis is there, the more you're really
considered to be part, be
the... anyway, I'll get to that in a second. Anyway, the basic
point first that I'm trying to address is what does it mean
to be עוסק בהספד osek b'hasped that it's affected by whether the
מת mes is there. But if the מת mes isn't there, then
to some degree you're less עוסק בהספד osek b'hasped and you can
first not even go off individually, to some degree as a group
you're less עוסק בהספד osek b'hasped if the מת mes isn't there,
and therefore you can first all say שמע and דאווען. daven. Now
as this group is saying שמע and דאווענינג, davening, what is the
אבל avel doing? So now remember the אבל avel is not even
an אבל avel yet, he's an אונן, onen, he's not allowed to
say שמע and דאווען. daven. So what does he do? So they
go ahead and they're saying שמע והוא יושב ודומם and he, the
אונן, onen, is sitting and being silent. הם עומדים ומתפללים, Heim omdim
u'mispallelim, they stand and pray, והוא עומד ומצדיק עליו את הדין. v'hu
omeid u'matzdik alav es hadin. He says צידוק הדין, Tziduk HaDin, which
is what an אבל, avel, an אונן onen says when he immediately
suffers a loss. ואומר, V'omer, and here's the language of the צידוק
הדין. Tziduk HaDin. רבונו של עולמים, Ribono Shel Olamim, or no, the
language of צידוק הדין Tziduk HaDin is really ברוך דיין האמת, Baruch
Dayan HaEmes, but here he says רבונו של עולמים, Ribono Shel Olamim,
חטאתי לפניך, chatasi lefanecha, I have sinned greatly before You, ולא נפרעתי
ממני אחד מאלף אלפי אלפים, v'lo nifrati mimeni echad m'elef alfei alafim,
and I haven't even been given my due punishment even for one
one-thousandth of what I've done. So meaning I accept the fact that
what I'm suffering is somehow
just. I realize how much I've sinned. יהי רצון מלפניך ה׳ אלהינו,
Yehi ratzon milfanecha Hashem Elokeinu, may it be Thy will שתגדור פרצותינו
ופרצות כל עמך בית ישראל ברחמים, shetigdor pirtzoseinu u'pirtzos kol amcha Beis
Yisrael b'rachamim, that you should close our breaches, you should seal our
breaches and the breaches of your people Israel with רחמים. rachamim. And
that is the צידוק הדין. Tziduk HaDin. Now the... well we'll talk
about what... in a minute, let's see what the גמרא Gemara responds.
אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, לא מיבעי ליה לאיניש למימר הכי. lo miba'ei
lei l'einish l'meimar hachi. People shouldn't say that. דאמר רבי שמעון בן
לקיש, D'amar Rabi Shimon ben Lakish, וכן תנא משמיה דרבי יוסי, v'chein
tana mishmei d'Rabi Yosi, לעולם אל יפתח אדם פיו לשטן. l'olam al
yiftach adam piv l'Satan. You should not open up your mouth. Good
Jewish
approach, poo poo poo and בלי עין הרע kein ayin hara and
all that. So you should not say something
that is asking for trouble, open up your mouth to the Satan.
So if you say I have not been received my punishment even
one thousandth of what I really deserve, so you're asking to be
punished. ואמר רב יוסף, v'amar Rav Yosef, מאי קרא, mai kra, where's
the פסוק? pasuk? שנאמר, Shene'emar, כמעט כסדום היינו לעמורה דמינו. k'meat k'Sedom
hayinu l'Amora daminu. Some פסוקים pesukim we read a little while ago
by תשעה באב. Tisha B'Av. We were almost like Sodom. מאי אהדר
להו נביא? Mai ahadar lehu navi? So what does the נביא navi
say in the next פסוק? pasuk? שמעו דבר ה׳ קציני סדום. Shim'u
devar Hashem ktzinei Sedom. He calls them officers of Sodom. You said
you were almost like Sodom, I'm going to call you Sodom. So
you're asking for trouble. Now but let me just say one thing.
So besides the asking for trouble issue, the problem of I'm a
little bothered with this aspect of the צידוק הדין Tziduk HaDin because
it frames what happened, and some people do think this way, as
punishment. And the צידוק הדין Tziduk HaDin is yes, it's punishment but
it's deserved punishment. Whereas, and there are people that very much feel
that way, when you speak to people sometimes in mourning and after
a loss and it's what did I do to deserve this, or
sometimes it's the opposite, I know I deserve this, but it's framed
all as
punishment. Whereas there's a question about צידוק הדין Tziduk HaDin like maybe
it's not about me, maybe it's about the person who died. And
so the what has to be מצדיק את הדין matzdik es hadin
is that it was right for him to die, or that I
don't understand why he died but I believe God that You're just.
So I know it's not what I'm saying, the idea of vindicating
God, which is what צידוק הדין Tziduk HaDin is, which is what
the ברוך דיין האמת Baruch Dayan HaEmes is, which is I can't
understand it, I'm deeply disturbed, but at some level ישתבח שמיה רבא,
Yis-tabach sh'mei raba, at some level I acknowledge that God is just.
That's the point of the צידוק הדין. Tziduk HaDin. But the question
is again is the focus on me or is it a focus
on the person who died? Is it like I deserve this even
though I don't understand it, or this person, it was his time
even though I don't understand why there was some sense of divine
justice. So that I think is very
challenging, the way this frames it very much in terms of the
person. Bobby, you wanted to say...
No, I'm just curious whether to say something like this isn't a
sense of humility, which you're taught is a good thing to have.
We're totally told that משה Moshe was the essence of humility.
You mean to say that I...
yeah. So to say I deserve something not because you have enormous
guilt about a specific series of things you've done, but because
you're part of a huge world and you're very small right now
in that world and I understand how great God is and how
small you are.
Yes, but... It's a little ironic that in talking about how small
you are, you're framing what happened as a punishment to you. It
wasn't a punishment for me.
The way it's framed is, I have not received, I I I
have sinned greatly against you and I have not received one one
thousandth of what I did, of what I deserve.
Why
are you bothering saying that if it isn't about you?
Then why isn't it like the there but for fortune type statement?
No. Because what do you do?
I don't think so.
Well because the thing continues in the plural, the the צדוק הדין
*Tzidduk HaDin*. Right.
So he starts,
well that's always, yes, but that's always the way it starts, you
know. המקום ינחם אתכם Hamakom yenachem eschem בתוך שאר אבלי ציון וירושלים
*Hamakom yenachem etchem betoch shear aveilei Tzion v'Yerushalayim* and sort of, you
know, broadens it. Anyway, the actual צדוק הדין *Tzidduk HaDin* that we
have is הצור תמים פעלו כי כל דרכיו משפט אל אמונה ואין
עול צדיק וישר הוא *Hatzur tamim poalo ki chol drachav mishpat el
emunah v'ein avel tzaddik veyashar hu*, צדיק בכל דרכיו *Tzaddik bechol drachav*,
right, nothing about me. Like whatever God has done, whoever is suffering
as a result, the person who died, everybody around him, whatever God
is doing is just. Here let's read it in ברוך הוא כי
אמת דינו ומשוטט הכל בעינו ומשלם לאדם חשבונו ודינו והכל כחכמתו דיין
אמת שמו *Baruch Hu ki emet dino umishotet hakol beino umishalem l'adam
cheshbono vdino vehakol k'chochmato Dayan emet shmo*, meaning God pays everybody what
they deserve, meaning it's about why the justice of this person having
died.
Why did, not about, you know, my loss, but about this person.
But you see that
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
is saying it's about the pain that I'm feeling at this moment
from the loss. Yeah, or finding the מת mes, *meit*. That is
what it sounds like. I mean it's very different, I mean
I don't understand how else do you
understand why I am framing it as
I've sinned greatly before you? The only way, the only other way,
is there but for the grace of God go I. Yes, and
so you know what, that guy died. I should I should also
be dead for my own sins. He died for his sins, I
should have died for my sins.
Okay, I like it. I appreciate that as a reframing.
And the death is the punishment, right? But what happens after the
death might be, might be punishment.
True. No, what do you mean? If it's about, if it's about
the person's loss, then the punishment is that I lost this person
close to me.
In terms of what we read now? Do we consider the death
itself a punishment? Yes. Or we're afraid for the punishment,
no, no, no, no, no. It's that when somebody dies, right, there's
a lot of questioning that goes on, right? What did I do
to deserve this? What did this person do to deserve this? Why
is God, you know, how is this just? And the amazing thing
about, you know, sort of all these issues, like in a way
it's like I should take one minute to say this, it's like
the counterbalance of the אונן *onen*. On the one hand we spoke
the other day that Rav Soloveitchik's understanding of why the אונן *onen*
is not just exempt from מצוות mitzvos *mitzvot*, but he really doesn't
do even basic stuff like making ברכות *brachot* or whatever, which is
never we say by עוסק במצוה *osek bamitzvah*, is because to some
extent a מצוה mitzvah. *mitzvah* is like an affirmation of meaning and
you actually are entitled or should be at this time, you know,
sort of, you know, be in this existential sense of like what
does life mean, what's this all about, and you know, and not
to be immediately moving into that affirmation of meaning by doing the
life of מצוות *mitzvot*. So on the one hand we sort of
acknowledge that and even sort of demand that, that you are allowed
that to yourself to experience that. And at the same time to
say that at some level even if I don't understand it, at
some level I still believe that God is just. So there's that
both, you know, we're not sort of telling you to, to not
have your questionings and your doubts and your issues and your struggles,
but that we, people have a lot of contradictory stuff going on
inside of them. You can have all of that and say, like,
I still believe or I still
would like to believe, I still, you know, strive to believe that
God is just. That's the קדיש *Kaddish* and that's the and that's
the צדוק הדין *Tzidduk HaDin* that we say.
Yes. And it's a continuation of the previous discussion because
in a way, if you can't question the rabbis then you certainly
can't...
Oh that's interesting.
The juxtaposition of those two stories might be.
Okay. I mean here אביי *Abaye* is questioning the תנא *Tanna* of
the ברייתא *braita*. Right, here אביי *Abaye* is questioning the תנא *Tanna*
of the ברייתא *braita*. That's a good point, right, it's a ברייתא
*braita* and אביי *Abaye* is modifying it. That's a very good point,
just on his own authority. It's a very good point, very good
point. Okay, now, so let's continue. קברו את המת וחזרו *Kavru et
hameit v'chazru*. So they buried him and then they're turning back. So
if they're able to say שמע *Shema* before it's time to stand
in the שורה *shura*, the row that accepts the mourners, they do,
and if not, they don't. אם יכולים להתחיל ולגמור כולה, אין *Im
yecholim lehatchil v'ligmor kullah, in*. So it sounds like only if they
can say the whole שמע *Shema* they do it. אבל פרק perek,
אחד או o, פסוק pasuk, אחד, לא *Aval perek echad o pasuk
echad, lo*. If they can just get in a פרק perek, *perek*
or פסוק pasuk, *pasuk*, then they don't. Why bother? You're not going
to be able to do the מצוה mitzvah, *mitzvah* anyway if you
can just get that in. And this gets to the question of
how much of שמע *Shema* is the biblical שמע *Shema*. ורמינהו *U'reminhu*
on this קברו את המת וחזרו *Kavru et hameit v'chazru*. They buried
the dead and they are turning, which they do now away from
the cemetery to do the line. אם יכולים להתחיל ולגמור אפילו פרק
perek, אחד או פסוק pasuk, אחד *Im yecholim lehatchil v'ligmor afilu perek
echad o pasuk echad*. If they can just do one פרק *perek*
or one פסוק pasuk *pasuk*, they should do it if they can
get that in before
they have to do the line. So גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says הכי
נמי קאמר *hachi nami ka'amar*. Fine, that's what the משנה *Mishnah* means.
אם יכולים להתחיל ולגמור אפילו פרק אחד או פסוק pasuk אחד *Im
yecholim lehatchil v'ligmor afilu perek echad o pasuk echad*. It says to
say it, it doesn't mean the whole thing, it means some minimum
amount, one פרק *perek* or one פסוק pasuk *pasuk*, עד שלא יגיעו
לשורה *ad shelo yagiu lashura*, before the line starts, יתחילו *yatchilu*, ואם
לאו לא יתחילו *v'im lav lo yatchilu*. Now again, does this prove
what's, is this a question of what is the biblical... biblical שמע?
It might be and then the גמרא Gemara is not concluding and
we've seen that issue before like רבי used to only say one
פרק, one פסוק, pasuk we've had others saying one פרק, so how
much of the שמע is biblical and if you can do the
biblical מצוה you do it and if not not. We're not going
to decide how much is biblical. It might be a פרק, might
be a פסוק, whatever it is that's the part that you have
to do. The other interesting question could be even if we said
you were not יוצא yotzei the biblical מצוה by doing a פסוק,
maybe you should do the whole פסוק because of קבלת עול מלכות
שמים. kabalas ol malchus shamayim. You know what does it mean to
not do קבלת עול מלכות שמים kabalas ol malchus shamayim although that
does not seem to be the focus of the גמרא. Gemara It
seems very much to be the question of being able to do
the מצוה. So let's continue now העומדים בשורה. ha'omdim bashurah. Those in
the line. Those on the inside are עוסק במצוה. They don't do
דאוונינג davening and שמע. Those on the outside can drop off, can
sort of go out one by one. תנו רבנן: שורה הרואה פנימה
פטורה. shurah haroah penimah peturah. The line that sort of is there's
multiple lines, the line that's on the inside track that's where the
mourners walk between, right? So they are פטור. patur. They are directly
עוסק במצוה and they do not do anything else. ושאינה רואה פנימה
חייבת. veshe'einah roah penimah chayaves. If they're not looking on the inside
חייבת, chayaves, they're obligated. רבי יהודה אומר: Rabbi Yehudah omer: הבא מחמת
האבל פטור מחמת עצמו חייב. haba machmas ha'avel patur machmas atzmo chayav.
He is broader. He says you know this question again how much
do these silent participants participate. So he says anybody that is there
for the sake of the mourners is פטור. If you're there for
the mourners you're עוסק במצוה even if you're not directly there and
saying המקום ינחם. Hamakom yenachem. But if you're there for yourself like
you say oh wow this is a big thing let me go
see what's going on or maybe you're there to be seen you
know or whatever reason you're there but it's not there for the
mourner then you're not considered עוסק במצוה. So that's a fascinating different
framing, right? Is עוסק במצוה like the direct act that you're doing,
are you saying המקום ינחם אתכם Hamakom yenachem eschem or maybe presence
is a type of an עוסק במצוה?
But maybe it's a
question of about more amorphous how do you measure what type of
presence is really present for them as opposed to present for you.
One wonders according to him let's say the guy's on the inside
track and you're saying המקום ינחם אתכם but you're still there just
for your own purposes would that be עוסק במצוה or not? But
it's a very different way of framing it. Okay so well that's
true but you're in the well okay. Okay now אמר רב יהודה
אמר רב: amar Rav Yehudah amar Rav: now we so that's about
מת meis, and עוסק במצוה and all of that. I'll just say
one thing before we switch to the next topic which is on
Sunday you did the issue about the שומרים shomrim of the מת
meis. and I should point out that right now as anybody I
assume people know like if somebody dies you know this whole idea
of שמירה shmirah of the מת met, and they hire somebody he
sits there like hours and hours and says תהילים Tehillim or whatever.
רב משה Rav Moshe says in an early תשובה tshuvah that actually
if there's no concern about something happening to the body because the
גמרא Gemara was concerned about whether there are rats and when there
are rats they could they could you know on a boat they
could go to the other side and דאוון. So רב משה Rav
Moshe says when there's no concern that something will really happen to
the body you don't need to be watching it. He says maybe
you need to watch it intermittently because like maybe if there aren't
rats maybe other types of things could happen but you certainly don't
need to be watching it constantly based on the גמרא Gemara we
said before. And now you know they keep the מת, met. they
keep it in this like freezer vault you know everything nothing's going
to happen to it. So maybe you say who knows the power
might go out but anyway according to רב משה Rav Moshe all
הלכה halachah would really demand would be that you like occasionally check
up to see that everything is okay and obviously we treat that
very differently. Also raises questions sometimes that can you have a non-Jewish
שומר shomer you know we've really like ritualized this act of שמירה
shmirah but based on the גמרא Gemara we saw earlier it is
far from clear. Okay so do you want to say something? Okay
so let's take a look now we shift gears to a very
different topic and a very important topic in הלכה. halachah. So אמר
רב יהודה אמר רב: amar Rav Yehudah amar Rav: this is going
to seem like it comes from nowhere but you'll see how we'll
circle back to our topic. המוציא כלאים בבגדו hamotzi kilayim bevigdo if
somebody finds walking on the street and sees that oh realizes that
they're wearing שעטנז. shatnez. It can happen you know like somebody told
me I bought this gorgeous dress or whatever and then I looked
at the label like wool and linen. So let's say you happen
to look at the label as you're wearing it in the middle
of the street. Okay פושטן אפילו בשוק poshtan afillu bashuk you gotta
rip it off yourself even in the middle of the street. Okay
presumably מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? אין חכמה ואין תבונה ואין עצה לנגד
ה'. ein chochmah ve'ein tevunah ve'ein eitzah leneged Hashem. There is no
wisdom there is no understanding there is no like you know counsel
before God. Don't make חשבונות. cheshbonos. If it's about and this really
Rachel does directly tie into the סוגיא sugya on the עמוד א':
amud aleph: כל מקום שיש חילול השם אין חולקין כבוד לרב. kol
makom sheyeish chillul Hashem ein cholkin kavod lerav. Wherever there's a concern
of desecration of God's name we don't show respect to the rabbi.
So you might think so they didn't say even a woman they
said even a rabbi right? You have to be walk naked in
the in the middle of the street because your כבוד הרב which
we were so much talking about back there and in some ways
implicitly connected it to כבוד of God because the whole issue about
חוני המעגל. But nevertheless that that is completely immaterial if it's an
issue about God's honor and God's honor being defined as doing an
עבירה aveirah even if it's not like public you're the only one
knowing you're doing the עבירה aveirah but it's an issue about God
your honor doesn't mean anything. Okay so now the גמרא Gemara says
מיתיבי meisivei so this is going to get into the central הלכתי
halachic discussion about כבוד הבריות. kevod habriyos. When does issues relating to
human dignity... will override certain halakhic considerations. Okay, so מיתיבי, Meisvei, I'll
ask you on this, and this is where why it's connected to
us. קברו את המת וחזרו וחזרו. Kevru es hameis vechazru vechazru. They
buried the dead and they're coming back to the city. ולפניהם שתי
דרכים, velifneihem shtei drachim, there are two paths. אחת טהורה ואחת טמאה.
achas tehora veachas tmeia. One is pure and one is impure, there's
a body buried under one of the paths. בא בטהורה, ba betehora,
if the other goes in the pure path, בוא עמו, bo imo,
you follow him בטהורה. betehora. בא בטמאה, ba betmeia, if the other
walks down the טמאה tmeia path, בוא עמו בטמאה, bo imo betmeia,
you follow him even presumably if you're a כהן. kohen. Why? משום
כבודו, mishum kevodo,
because of the honor that you have to show to the other.
You don't want to abandon the other. So for the sake of
the כבוד of this other person, you actually can violate this law.
So how's that different than what we just said? לימא, Leima, why
not say אין חכמה ואין תבונה ואין עצה לנגד ה׳, ein chochma
ve'ein tevuna ve'ein eitza leneged Hashem, that, you know, no חכמה chochma
is before God. You don't, if it's a מצוה, you don't violate
it under any issue, under any circumstance. So תרגמה רבי אבא בבית
הפרס דרבנן. Targama Rabi Abba beveisa pras derabbanan. We don't mean that
it's a literally a טמא tamei path and that there's a body
underneath it and the כהן kohen would violate the biblical law. We
mean it's a rabbinically טמא tamei path. What's rabbinically טמא? tamei? This
thing called בית הפרס. beisa pras. What is that? דאמר רב יהודה
אמר שמואל מנפח אדם בית הפרס והולך. de'amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel
menapeiach adam beisa pras veholeich. You can blow, you know, the dust
of a בית הפרס beisa pras and walk through it. A בית
הפרס beisa pras is basically an area where a grave has been
plowed over in a field, and you're concerned—it's not like you know
there's a body here and anytime you walk over here you're becoming
טמא, tamei, but you're concerned that there are little chips of bone
in the field. So and that's seen as only a rabbinic concern.
Maybe biblically we would assume you're not going to touch the chips
of bone; the chips will be too small to be a problem.
But rabbinically we say you can't walk through the field. And the
only way you can walk through the field is if like you
blow the dirt right in front of you before you take the
next step to make sure that you're blowing away any possible chips
of bone. So anyway, the point though is that we would not
have allowed that if it was biblical. Clearly it's only a rabbinic
concern. So we allow you to violate a rabbinic concern for the
issue of כבוד הבריות. kevod habriyos. And this is the very basic
principle, that כבוד הבריות kevod habriyos overrides not biblical law, but it
does override rabbinic law. And that's going to be the theme here,
and that's a very important halakhic principle. So let's take a look.
ואמר רב יהודה בר אשי משמיה דרב בית הפרס שנדש טהור. ve'amar
Rav Yehuda bar Ashi mishmeih deRav beisa pras shenidash tahor. Similarly, if
a בית הפרס beisa pras was trampled through, then it's טהור, tahor,
then somehow you can assume that there's no chips to worry about.
Okay. תא שמע, Ta shema, let's still try to prove this case.
דאמר רבי אלעזר בר צדוק מדלגין היינו על גבי ארונות של מתים
לקראת מלכי ישראל. de'amar Rabi Elazar bar Tzadok medalgin hayinu al gabei
aronot shel meisim likras malchei Yisrael. We used to hop over the
coffins of the dead לקראת מלכי ישראל, likras malchei Yisrael, in order
to greet
Jewish kings that would be coming our way. I wonder where רבי
אלעזר בר צדוק Rabi Elazar bar Tzadok was dealing with Jewish kings,
but anyway, I don't know, was that how early was he? He
wasn't in the time of the חשמונאים, Chashmonaim, was he? I don't
think so. Anyway, so whoever מלכי ישראל malchei Yisrael is, ולא לקראת
מלכי ישראל בלבד אמרו, velo likras malchei Yisrael bilvad amru, not only
for Jewish kings, אלא אפילו לקראת מלכי עובדי כוכבים, ela afilu likras
malchei ovdei kochavim, we would even do it for non-Jewish kings, שאם
יזכה, she'im yizkeh, that if you merit to live in a time
when there's a Jewish monarch, when there's ימות המשיח, yemos hamashiach, יבחין
בין מלכי ישראל למלכי עובדי כוכבים, yavchin bein malchei Yisrael lemalchei ovdei
kochavim, if you see non-Jewish kings and then you can compare what
Jewish kings are like, then it'll be, you know, that it'll be
a greater appreciation for Jewish kingship. Anyway, the point being, we would
jump over ארונות aronot to greet these kings, which would be כבוד
המלכות, kevod hamalchus, but they were כהנים. kohanim. So how could they
do it? Okay, we know he was a כהן. kohen. So how
could you do it? So the גמרא says
אמאי, Amai, why could he do this? לימא אין חכמה ואין תבונה
ואין עצה לנגד ה׳, leima ein chochma ve'ein tevuna ve'ein eitza leneged
Hashem, no חכמה chochma is before God. So כדרבא, kiderava, דאמר רבא
דבר תורה אהל שיש בו חלל טפח חוצץ בפני הטומאה. de'amar Rava
devar Torah ohel sheyesh bo challal tefach chotzeitz bifnei hatuma. No, here's
why they could jump over, because biblically, if there is a טפח,
tefach, a handbreadth, like, you know, between the top of the—the lid
of the ארון, aron, let's say, over the מת, there's a handbreadth,
then the handbreadth makes it a roof and it stops the טומאה
tuma from going out of the ארון. aron. ושאין בו חלל טפח
אינו חוצץ בפני הטומאה, veshe'ein bo challal tefach eino chotzeitz bifnei hatuma,
and if there's no handbreadth, it does not stop and the טומאה,
tuma, as it were, goes through the roof of the ארון aron
and goes up to the sky. ורוב ארונות יש בהן חלל טפח,
verov aronot yesh bahen challal tefach, most coffins have the טפח tefach
opening. וגזרו על שיש בהן משום שאין בהן, vegazru al sheyesh bahen
mishum she'ein bahen, and they said that even those that have the
טפח, tefach, you should treat them as if they don't, and you
should be strict and assume that there might be a problem. ומשום
כבוד מלכים לא גזרו בהן, umishum kevod melachim lo gazru bahen, because
of כבוד המלך kevod hamalech they did not make this גזירה. gezeira.
So the answer again being this is only a rabbinic problem, you
can override a rabbinic problem for כבוד הבריות, kevod habriyos, not a
biblical. But one minute, this is—this should be a shock, because we're
always taught, of course, that כהנים kohanim can't go into a cemetery,
even discussions about flying over a cemetery, you know, and the completeness
of it is that this is all biblical, that you walk over
a grave and the טומאה, tuma, anytime you're directly over the grave,
the טומאה tuma goes straight through. Here we're saying that in principle,
if there's a טפח, tefach, you know, between, you know, from the
roof... yeah, inside the coffin, then there is a—then it stops the
טומאה, tuma, right? So how do you make sense of this? Why
do we say that it's all biblical? So the answer תוספות Tosafot
says is that there's really a separate הלכה halakha that the גמרא
is somewhat ignoring or bracketing, which is that the entire coffin becomes
considered to be
an extension of
the
מת. If the coffin actually has an opening, then you don't really
treat it as a coffin and then actually the lid of the
coffin stops the טומאה. tumah. But if the coffin is sealed on
all sides, that’s תוספות says what the case in the גמרא is.
But if the coffin is sealed on all sides, it’s considered an
extension of the מת, and therefore it doesn’t stop the טומאה tumah
and the טומאה tumah goes straight up. So just understand why we
basically for our cemeteries and walking over cemeteries is דאורייתא, d'oraissa, here
Rav was able to say it’s rabbinic if he was assuming a
scenario of a non-sealed, of a coffin that was not completely sealed.
Why that would be the case, I don’t know. Yes.
In ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael they don’t use coffins.
So that’s even more of an issue, there’s not even a possibility
that there’s something to stop the מת. The only possibility is you’ve
got him in a coffin and you say the lid of the
coffin stops the טומאה. tumah.
Also, I just looked up Rabbi Elyashiv and he said תודוס is
a contemporary of יוחנן בן זכאי. Yochanan ben Zakkai.
So there were certainly non-Jewish kings around, Caesar. There were non-Jewish kings.
אגריפס. Agrippa. What? אגריפס, Agrippa, I see. Uh-huh, that’s a good point.
Okay. All right. Yes. What are we talking?
We're talking in this case of ארון שיש בו חלל טפח? aron
sheyesh bo chalal tapach?
Yes, and therefore it was only a rabbinic problem. Okay, so let's
just do one more point about this. So the גמרא says like
this. תא שמע, Tashma, come and hear. גדול כבוד הבריות שדוחה לא
תעשה שבתורה. gadol kvod habriyot shedocheh lo taaseh shebatorah. Here is a
great principle: כבוד הבריות kvod habriyot is so great it overrides rabbinic,
a biblical prohibition. You see it does override biblical prohibitions, you don't
have to take off your dress. There you go, exactly. למה, lamah,
לימא אין חכמה ואין תבונה ואין עצה לנגד ה׳, leima ein chochmah
veein tvunah veein eitzah leneged Hashem, no חכמה chochmah is before God,
why should כבוד הבריות kvod habriyot override? תרגמה רב בר שבא קמי
דרב כהנא, targemah Rav Bar Shava kamei d'Rav Kahana, so he explains
it to mean בלאו דלא תסור. belav d'lo tassur. We don't mean
literally every biblical prohibition, we mean a very specific biblical prohibition. The
biblical prohibition of not violating what the rabbis say, לא תסור מן
הדבר. lo tassur min hadavar. So meaning you can override rabbinic law,
we frame it as biblical
because we're supposed to
biblically listen to the rabbis, but the rabbis have some latitude to
tell us when we have to listen to them and when we
don't. So yes, you can, but in the end it really means
you can override rabbinic prohibitions, not biblical. So the גמרא says אחיכו
עלי, achiku alai, they laughed about this. They thought it was a
joke. לאו דלא תסור דאורייתא היא. lav d'lo tassur d'oraissa hi. What
do you mean? If you're really violating that biblical prohibition, it's still
biblical. So, I'm sorry, no, right, well that's the point I'm going
to say. אמר רב כהנא גברא רבה אמר מילתא לא תחיכו עליה,
amar Rav Kahana gavra raba amar milta la techiku alei, a great
person says something you should not laugh on him. So why,
so what does it mean? כל מילי דרבנן אסמיכינהו על לא תסור.
kol mili d'rabanan asmichinu al lo tassur. We don't mean like a
straight violation of לא תסור, lo tassur, we mean rabbinic law. Okay,
but every rabbinic law ultimately has the prohibition of לא תסור lo
tassur standing somewhere in the
background. ומשום כבודו שרו רבנן, umishum kvodo shar rabanan, and the rabbis
waive the need to do the rabbinic law because of כבוד הבריות.
kvod habriyot. So I don't mean literally if you're really confronting a
direct לא תסור. lo tassur. Now what would it mean to directly
confront? So some for example say that why is it that every
time I violate a rabbinic law I violate a biblical law? Because
I'm not supposed to stray from what the rabbis say. So the
basic answer is that to violate לא תסור lo tassur comes through
an act of sort of rejecting the rabbinic authority and violating the
law. I violate this because I don't think I have to listen
to the rabbis. That's the לא תסור. lo tassur. If I violated
it because I, you know, my יצר הרע yetzer hara got the
better of me or I made a mistake or because of כבוד
הבריות, kvod habriyot, I'm not really violating לא תסור, lo tassur, okay?
Because I really acknowledge the rabbis' power, I'm just violating this law
for whatever reason. So they're saying yes, you're right, this is, you're
not really violating the biblical law, but we call it biblical because
the לא תסור lo tassur stands somewhere in the background. But at
the end of the day the rule is the same: you can
override rabbinic law for כבוד הבריות, kvod habriyot, not biblical. I know
we're a little over, I just have to read one more line
about this. But the rabbis are willing to waive their things. So
let's read one more. תא שמע והתעלמת מהם. Tashma ve-hisalamta mehem. This
is about a returning an אבידה. avedah. And the פסוק says, the
פסוק is with a question mark: והתעלמת מהם? ve-hisalamta mehem? Do you
think you could hide yourself from an אבידה? avedah? No, you have
to return it. Don't hide your eye. But the rabbis read it
with, not the question mark, they read it as a period: והתעלמת
מהם. ve-hisalamta mehem. There are times you do hide yourself from the
אבידה, avedah, you don't return it. פעמים שאתה מתעלם מהם ופעמים שאי
אתה מתעלם מהם. pe'amim she-atah mitalem mehem u-fe'amim she-ein atah mitalem mehem.
היכי דמי? haikei dami? What's the case? אם היה כהן והיא בבית
הקברות. im hayah Kohen ve-hi beveit hakvarot. If there was an אבידה
avedah lost object in a cemetery, obviously you're not going to violate
and get the lost object. או, okay, so that's in itself not
so interesting. Here's what's interesting: היה זקן ואינו לפי כבודו. hayah zaken
ve-eino le-fi kvodo. You are an old person, so stoop down and
pick up this lost object, this quarter on the street? That's something
that is not appropriate for the dignity, for your dignity and respect.
או שהיתה מלאכתו מרובה משל חברו. o she-haytah melachto merubah mishel chaveiro.
Or look, the guy's going to have to pay me back for
lost wages when I return his object. Let's say the money he's
going to have to pay me back will exceed the cost of
the object. So then I'm not going to return it. But that's
out of a concern for him, not for me. In those cases,
לכך נאמר והתעלמת מהם. l'kach ne'emar v'hitalamta mehem. So case one and
three are not so interesting for our purposes. I don't return it
if I'll violate, I don't report it if the cost will exceed
the benefit. But the second case is interesting. I don't return it
if it's going to impinge on my dignity, on my honor. Well,
there's a biblical מצווה mitzvah that I am not doing because of
because of my honor. Shouldn't that serve as a paradigm? So גמרא
says, אמאי? amai? Why is that true? לימא אין חכמה ואין תבונה
ואין עצה נגד ה'? lema ein chochmah v'ein tevunah v'ein etzah neged
Hashem? What about saying there's no חכמה chochmah before God? So גמרא
says, שאני התם דכתיב והתעלמת מהם. shani hasam de-chtiv v'hitalamta mehem. There
it's different. The פסוק tells you, that's a special case, it's an
exception. So the גמרא says, וניגמר מיניה? v'nigmar minei? Why make it
an exception? Make it the rule. Let's use that as a paradigm.
So it says, איסורא מממונא לא ילפינן. issura mi-mamona lo yalfinan. We
don't learn איסורא, issura, a prohibition, from monetary issues. Returning an אבידה
avedah is a מצווה mitzvah but at the end of the day,
it's about money. So it's always a question, right, at what time,
how you look at money issues? Do you look at them through
the מצווה mitzvah lens or through the money lens? Like why is
not every single case of if I might owe you money and
I don't have to pay you, why not? Because we say המוציא
מחברו עליו הראיה. hamotzi mei-chaveiro alav ha-rayah. Unless I'm sure I owe
you, I don't have to pay. Why don't we say it's a
ספק איסור גזל safek issur geizel and therefore I have to pay?
So somehow money issues are dealt with first with a certain type
of their own standard and they're not immediately transferred into the consideration
about the מצוות and עבירות. aveiros. They're first judged as a money
case. Well, if it's a question about money, your dignity outweighs that
person's money. We don't say your dignity outweighs the מצווה. mitzvah. We
address it first in terms of the significance of the money issue
and then whether it's a מצווה mitzvah or not or whether it's
an עבירה aveirah or not sort of flows from how we define
it in that standard. So at this stage, we are asserting that
it only overrides rabbinic law, between some of these cases that are
found biblical into rabbinic. We said, yeah, there's like a דאורייתא, d'oraisa,
לא תסור lo sasur somewhere lurking in the background but basically only
rabbinic. But we did find one case of biblical, not returning the
אבידה, avedah, which we have tried to sort of bracket by saying
it's only a monetary issue. We will finish this סוגיא sugya tomorrow
and discuss what is the conclusion of when does כבוד הבריות kevod
habriyos override or not.